Guide to the P. D. Ouspensky Memorial Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
P. D. Ouspensky memorial collection
1913-2010
MS 840
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
58.27
The collection consists of reports of meetings of P. D. Ouspensky with his followers in London (1921-1947) and his manuscripts of books and articles in Russian, French, and English. Included are In Search of the Miraculous, New Model of the Universe, and Tertium Organum. Also in the collection are printed copies of Ouspensky's books in various languages, selected articles by others on Ouspensky, and photographs.
Uspenskiĭ, P. D. (Petr Demʹi︠a︡novich), 1878-1947
Conditions Governing Access
These records are available for research.
In series I, original typescriptsof meeting reports are too fragile to be used. Photostatic copies of these records are available for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Tatiana Nagro and others, 1976-1992; gift of Tatiana Nagro, 2000; gift of the Society for the Study of Normal Psychology, 1998; gift of H. W. Kropholler, 2003; gift of William A. Simon, 2003. Gift of Daniel Cerqueiro, 2010.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and additions: I. Reports of Meetings. II. Writings. III. Writings by Others.
Biographical / Historical
P. D. Ouspensky was a journalist based in Russia, and travelled extensively in Europe and the Near East. He met George I. Gurdjieff in 1915 and became his follower. Ouspensky broke with Gurdjieff in 1918, left Russia in 1920 and went to Constantinople, and then went to London in 1921 where he founded the Historico-Psychological Society.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of reports of meetings of P. D. Ouspensky with his followers in London (1921-1947) and his manuscripts of books and articles in Russian, French, and English. Included are In Search of the Miraculous, New Model of the Universe, and Tertium Organum. Also in the collection are printed copies of Ouspensky's books in various languages, selected articles by others on Ouspensky, and photographs.
Accruals
Writings by others about Ouspensky will no longer be added to the collection as of August 2010.
Occultism; Gurdjieff, Georges Ivanovitch, 1872-1949; Uspenskiĭ, P. D. (Petr Demʹi︠a︡novich), 1878-1947
- REPORTS OF MEETINGS, Series I
  - Original Transcripts
    Conditions Governing Access
    These records are too fragile to be used; please use electrostatic copies instead.
    - Typescripts
      - 1921-1925 (Box 1)
      - 1928-1935 March (Box 2)
      - 1935 April-December (Box 3)
      - 1936 January-October (Box 4)
      - 1936 November-1938 January 19 (Box 5)
      - 1938 January 20-May 17 (Box 6)
      - 1938 May 18-September 9 (Box 7)
      - 1938 September 13-1939 January 17 (Box 8)
      - 1939 January 19-March (Box 9)
      - 1939 April-November 19 (Box 10)
      - 1939 November 22-1940 April (Box 11)
      - 1940 May-1942 September 9 (Box 12)
      - 1942 September 15-1944 February 9 (Box 13)
      - 1944 February 15-1945 February (Box 14)
      - 1945 March-1947 March 5 (Box 15)
      - 1947 March 12-June 18, undated (Box 16)
  - Electrostatic Copies
    - Typescripts
      - 1921-1925 (Box 17)
      - 1928-1935 February (Box 18)
      - 1935 March-October 16 (Box 19)
      - 1935 October 17-1936 May 19 (Box 20)
      - 1936 May 20-1937 October 6 (Box 21)
      - 1937 September 23-1938 February 9 (Box 22)
      - 1938 February 10-May 17 (Box 23)
      - 1938 May 18-July (Box 24)
      - 1938 September-November 10 (Box 25)
      - 1938 November 15-1939 February 25 (Box 26)
      - 1939 February 27-May 25 (Box 27)
      - 1939 May 30-November (Box 28)
      - 1939 December-1940 April 11 (Box 29)
      - 1940 April 16-1941 November (Box 30)
      - 1941 December-1943 April (Box 31)
      - 1943 May-1944 April (Box 32)
      - 1944 May-1945 April 18 (Box 33)
      - 1945 April 25-1947 March 5 (Box 34)
      - 1947 March 12-June 18, undated (Box 35)
      - "Extracts for Reading" (Box 35)
      - "Constitution of the Historico-Psychological Society" (Box 35)
      - "The Law of Three", 1935-1940 (Box 35)
- WRITINGS, Series II
  - Manuscripts
    - "About Mechanicalness", undated (Box 36)
    - "Atis, the Bloodless Victim" (in Russian), undated (Box 36)
    - "The Good Devil" (extract from translation), 1949 (Box 36)
    - "In Search of the Miraculous: Fragments of an Unknown Teaching"
      - In Russian
        - Introduction, 1926, 1927, 1928 (Box 36)
        - Introduction, 1928 (Box 37, Folder 1851-1853)
        - Chapter II, 1931 (Box 37, Folder 1854)
        - Chapters 2-3, 9-10, 12-17, 1932 (Box 37, Folder 1855-1865)
        - Chapters 18-19, unidentified, 1932 (Box 38)
        - Chapter I, 1934 (Box 38)
        - Table of contents, chapters 1-14, commentary, undated (Box 38)
        - Unidentified, undated (Box 38)
      - In English
        - Introduction, 1925, 1926 1927 (Box 39)
        - Chapter 13, 1927 (Box 39)
        - Chapters 2-3, 1930 (Box 39)
        - Chapter 1, 1931 (Box 39)
        - Introduction, [pre-1932?] (Box 39)
        - Chapter 1, [pre-1932?1 (Box 39)
        - Chapters 1-8, 10-13, 1932 (Box 39)
        - Chapters 14-16, 1932 (Box 40)
        - Chapter 11, 1933 (Box 40)
        - Chapter 1, 1934 (Box 40)
        - Chapters 13-18, 1935 (Box 40)
        - Chapter 3, [c. 1941-1946] (Box 40)
        - Introduction, undated (Box 40)
        - Chapters 1-2, 4-5, undated (Box 40)
        - Chapters 6-7, 9-11, 13-14, undated (Box 41)
        - Unidentified, undated (Box 41)
    - "The Inner Circle: Two Lectures on 'The Brink' and on 'Superman'", 1913 (Box 41)
    - "Letters from Russia", 1919 (Box 41)
    - "A New Model of the Universe"
      - In French
        - Introduction, 1931 (Box 41)
        - Chapters 1-2, 1932 (Box 41)
      - In English
        - Loose pages, 1931 (Box 41)
        - Preface, 1933 (Box 41)
    - "Notes on Work", undated (Box 41)
    - "Occult Stories: 2. Talks with the Well-Meaning Devil", undated (Box 41)
    - "On the Superman" (in Russian), undated (Box 42, Folder 1743)
    - "Ouspensky Papers Vol. I", [c. 1923-1947] (Box 42)
    - "Ouspensky Papers Vol. II", [c. 1923-1947] (Box 42)
    - "Psychological Lectures", 1936 (Box 42)
    - "Self-Will", 1955 (Box 42)
    - "The Sincere Narrations of a Pilgrim to his Spiritual Father", undated (Box 42)
    - "The Symbolism of the Tarot": annotated tarot deck and The Key to the Tarot by Arthur E. Waite, 1936 (Box 42)
    - "Talks with the Devil" (in Russian), 1916 (Box 42)
    - "Tertium Organum"
      - Chapters 8-23 (first rough translation), [pre-1944?] (Box 43)
      - Translator's correspondence and notes, 1944 (Box 43)
      - Translation by Mme. E. Kadloubovsky
        - Chapters 1-18, 1947 July (Box 43)
        - Chapters 19-23, 1947 July (Box 44)
        - Loose pages, undated (Box 44)
        - Summary, undated (Box 44)
        - Translator's notes, undated (Box 44)
    - "Transformism and Psycho-Transformism", undated (Box 44)
    - Untitled discussion of language, published in Transition, No. 23, 1935 Jul, 1934 (Box 44)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 44)
    - untitled set of drawings by P.D. Ouspensky, with Explanatory notes by Margaret Capper, undated (Box 44)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 44)
  - Books
    - The Fourth Way, 1957 (Box 45)
    - A Further Record Chiefly of Extracts from Meetings Held by P. D. Ouspensky between 1928 and 1945, 1952 (Box 45)
    - In Search of the Miraculous
      - English translation, 1949 (Box 45)
      - French translation, 1950 (Box 46)
      - Spanish translation, 1952, 1968 (Box 46)
      - Hebrew translation, 1977 (Box 47)
    - Letters from Russia 1919, 1978 (Box 47)
    - Memory, 1953 (Box 47)
    - Negative Emotions, 1953 (Box 47)
    - A New Model of the Universe
      - English translation, 1931 (Box 47)
      - Dutch translation, 1933 (Box 47)
      - Spanish translation, 1950 (Box 48)
      - German translation, 1970 (Box 48)
      - Spanish translation, 1977 (Box 48)
    - Notes on the Gospel of St. John, 1949 (Box 48)
    - Notes on Work, 1957 (Box 48)
    - Psychological Lectures 1934-1940, undated (Box 49)
    - The Psychology of Man's Possible Evolution
      - In English (2 copies), 1950 (Box 49)
      - French translation, 1952 (Box 49)
      - Danish translation, 1952 (Box 49)
      - Spanish translation, 1952 (Box 49)
      - Finnish translation, 1969 (Box 49)
      - Italian translation, 1972 (Box 49)
      - In English, 1973 (Box 49)
      - Danish translation, 1975 (Box 49)
    - A Record of Some Meetings held by P. D. Ouspensky between 1930 and 1947, 1951 (Box 49)
    - Strange Life of Ivan Osokin
      - In English, 1947, 1948 (Box 50)
      - Danish translation, 1948 (Box 50)
      - Spanish translation, 1950 (Box 50)
    - Surface Personality, 1954 (Box 50)
    - Symbolism of the Tarot (in Russian), 1912, 1917 (Box 50)
      - English translation, 1913 (Box 50A)
      - English translation, 1976 (Box 51)
    - Tertium Organum(in Russian), 1931 (Box 51)
      - English transaction, 1950 (Box 51)
      - Spanish transaction, 1950 (Box 51)
      - English transaction, 1961 (Box 51)
      - Spanish transaction, 1970, 1977 (Box 52)
      - German transaction, 1973 (Box 52)
- WRITINGS BY OTHERS, Series III
  - Writings by Others: Add. 1983
    - Anderson, William
      - (editor), The Bridge, 1978 winter (Box 53)
      - "From the Superfluous Man to the Superman", undated (Box 53)
    - Barnes, Carman Neal
      - "Miracles Can Happen: The Way Out for Modern Man", undated (Box 53)
      - "Strange Life of Ivan Osokin: A Play in Three Acts", undated (Box 53)
    - Bechhofer, C.E.: In Deniken's Russia and the Caucasus,1919-20; with additional material mentioning Denikin, 1921, 1974 (Box 53)
    - Bland, Rosamund: Extracts from Nine Letters Written by Rosamund Bland at the Beginning of P. D. Ouspensky's London Work in 1921 (Box 53)
    - Brochaus and Efron: Russian Encyclopaedic Dictionary, "Transformism", undated (Box 53)
    - de Popp, Robert S.: Conversations with Madame Ouspensky 1939-40 at Lyne, 1974 (Box 53)
    - Driscoll, Walter: "Gurdjieff: A Bibliographical Document of His Work and Influence", 1979 (Box 53)
    - Ferapontoff, Boris: "Constantinople Notes", undated (Box 53, Folder 1825b)
    - Gunn, Neil M.: "The Miraculous", 1968 (Box 53)
    - Gurdjieff, G.I.: untitled lecture, [1923 March 5?] (Box 53, Folder 1827)
    - Needleman, _____: summaries of eight books by P.D. Ouspensky, undated (Box 53)
    - Priestley, J.B.: Time and the Conways and Other Plays, 1974 (Box 53)
    - Rabeneck, Nicolai:"'Superfluous Men in Russian Literature, or the Ancestry of Ivan Osokin'", 1960 (Box 53)
    - "Two Trends of Thought in Russian Literature,", 1974 (Box 53)
    - Roles, Francis C.: The Unity of Conscious Experience, 1977 (Box 54)
    - Seton, Marie: "The Case of P.D. Ouspensky,", 1962 (Box 54)
    - Taylor, Merrily E. (editor): Remembering Pyotr Demianovich Ouspensky, with notes, drafts, 1978 (Box 54)
    - Tempelrey, H.W.V. (editor): A History of the Peace Conference of Paris, Vol. III, "Chronological Summary", 1920 (Box 54)
    - Urussoff, Prince C.D.: "Notes of a Governor,", 1903-1904 (Box 54)
    - Vernadsky, W.: "The Biosphere" (translation and appendix by Gerald Palmer), [post-1917] (Box 54)
    - "Glimpses of Truth" (read to P.D. Ouspensky by a student of Gurdjieff; in Russian), 1914 (Box 54)
    - Reminiscences about P.D. Ouspensky, 1951-1978, undated (Box 54)
- ADDITIONS, Series IV
  Scope and Contents
  Includes additional material received from 1983 to 1988 from multiple donors.
  - Miscellanea: 1983 addition
    - Correspondence, 1922, 1927, 1940, 1980 (Box 55)
    - Photographs, 1914-1927, undated (Box 55)
    - P.D. Ouspensky Centenary Exhibition at Yale University Library: posters, notes, and copies of manuscripts, photographs, and labels, 1978 (Box 55A)
      General note
      Folio
  - Writings: Manuscripts: 1983 addition
    - "Atis, the Bloodless Victim" (in English), undated (Box 55)
  - Writings: Books: 1983 addition
    - Conscience: The Search for Truth, 1979 (Box 55)
    - The Fourth Way
      - In English, 1971 (Box 55)
      - In Dutch translation, 1978 (Box 55)
      - In German translation, 1983 (Box 55)
    - In Search of the Miraculous
      - Portuguese translation, undated (Box 56)
    - A New Model of the Universe
      - English translation, 1934 (Box 56)
      - English translation, 1971 (Box 56)
      - Spanish translation, 1980 (Box 56)
    - The Psychology of Man's Possible Evolution
      - Hebrew translation, 1962 (Box 56)
      - In English, 1978 (Box 56)
    - The Symbolism of the Tarot, 1913 (Box 56)
    - Tertium Organum
      - English translation, 1947, 1981 (Box 56)
  - Writings: Manuscripts: 1984 addition
    - "The Temple" (poem translated from the Russian by P.D. Ouspensky, n.d.; copy), 1984 (Box 56)
  - Writings by Others: 1985 additions
    - [Ross, J.P.?] A Recapitulation of the Lord's Prayer, Accession 1986-M-0033, 1985 (Box 57)
    - A Point in the Work, Accession 1986-M-0095, 1985 (Box 57)
  - Papers and printed material given by the Gurdjieff Foundation, New York, 1864-1937 (Box 57–58)
  - Oversized (Box 58A)
  - Two pamphlets by Steven Barrett Perkins
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Received from Steven Barrett Perkins, 1987 November 12.
    - Chess, Stonehenge, and The Bhagavad Vita: Introduction to the Work of P. D. Ouspensky, 1986 (Box 58)
    - Chess, Metaphysics and Mathematics, 1986 (Box 58)
  - Autograph letter, signed, to P.D. Ouspensky from Eve Pryor, undated (Box 58)
    Received from Reference Department, Sterling Memorial Library, 1988 May 16.
- Additional Material, Accession 1990-M-038; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1990 March
  Received from: Tatiana Nagro, 1990 Feb 2
  - The Cosmology of Man's Possible Evolution, the Cosmological Lectures 1934-1940 (2 copies), 1989 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - The Psychology of Man's Possible Evolution and the Cosmology of Man's Possible Evolution (2 copies), 1989 (Box 59, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1903-1950s, 1975-1979, undated; Accession 1990-M-071; 2.50 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1990 Sep
  Received from: Barbara Phillips, 1990 May 4
  - Reports of Meetings
    - Photocopies of records of meetings, 1928, 1934-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
    - Carbons of records of meetings of the Historico-Psychological Society, 1942 May 5, 1945 January 7-September 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Photocopies of A Further Record Chiefly of Extracts from Meetings Held by P. D. Ouspensky between 1928 and 1945, pp. 1-161, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Annotated copy of early revision of the constitution of the Historico-Psychological Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "The Constitution of the Historico-Psychological Society" (10 duplicate copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Writings
    - "Law of Three", undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Photocopies of some pages of "Law of the Three," box 35, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Papers relating to Triads, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Schools, Three Lines of Work", 1935 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Paper on the subject of negative attitudes, [pre-1928] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Paper on the subject of the Devil, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "Diagram of Everything Living," in Russian; also known as "Step Diagram", undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Photocopy of "Commentary to Food Diagram", 1939 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Letters from Russia," The New Age, photocopies, 1919 September 4-December 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Russian poem on the nature of God, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Introduction to Fragments, photocopies of draft (pp.1-77), 1924 December- 1925 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Introduction to Fragments, photocopies of revised drafts (pp.2-90), [1924-1925?] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Carbon of draft of "Occult Stories": 2. "The Good Devil", undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "The Sincere Narrations of a Pilgrim to his Spiritual Father"; early draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "The Sincere Narrations of a Pilgrim to his Spiritual Father"; later draft (2 carbon copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "The Sincere Narrations of a Pilgrim to his Spiritual Father"; 2nd copy of later draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Glossary of the System, vocabulary, 1930 March 6, 1938 November 18, 1932 undated (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - Glossary of the System: definitions, dictionary, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Carbon of draft of The Fourth Way (earlier title: The Way Out); chapters 1-4, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Carbon of draft of The Fourth Way (earlier title: The Way Out); chapters 5-8, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Carbon of draft of The Fourth Way (earlier title: The Way Out); chapters 9-12, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Carbon of draft of The Fourth Way (earlier title: The Way Out); chapters 13-16, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Papers relating to Gurdjieff, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Papers re: G.I. Gurdjieff's American lectures; index, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Introductory Part: "The Root of Philosophy"; Explanatory Part: "The Method of Philosophy"; Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Diagrams K.IV. 30, 44, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Translations by Mme. E. Kadloubovsky of assorted papers, 1920s-1950s, undated (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
    - Between Two Births - Diary of a Witness to the Third World War; English translation of "Entre Deux Néants - Journal d'un témoin de la Troisieme Guerre Mondiale" (unidentified author), undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Photocopies of unsorted papers, 1934, 1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - Unsorted papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
  - Writings of Others
    - "Man's Task and His Reward: A New concept of Human Destiny Based Upon the Teaching of Gurdjieff," six lectures given by J.G. Bennett; including supplementary questions and answers, 1954 March 8-April 12 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Ferapontoff, Boris: notes on Ouspensky's meetings in Constantinople; photocopies, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Recherches sur L'Origine et la Nature des Mystères d'Éleusis, par M.P. Foucart (photocopy), undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Study of the Origin and Nature of the Eleusinian Mysteries, by M.P. Foucart; English translation by Michèle Larue, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - "Study of the Origin and Nature of the Eleusinian Mysteries," by M.P. Foucalt; 2 carbon copies, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Typescript for unpublished book on the Bible by Maurice Nicoll; possibly titled Time and Eternity, 1929, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Diary of the War (1940-1943) "by Maurice Nicoll, 1940 July 8-December 31 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Commentaries by Maurice Nicoll, 1953, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "Notes of a Governor, "by Prince C.D. Urussoff, pp. 1-75 of typescript, 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "Notes of a Governor," by Prince C.D. Urussoff, pp. 76-301 (2 copies), 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "Notes of a Governor," carbons (folder 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - The Biosphere, by W. Vernadsky; preface to the French edition and the Russian edition, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - The Biosphere, by W. Vernadsky; translation of pp.111-232; summary of; appendix, post-1917 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Geochemistry, by W. Vernadsky; typescript, [1922-1923?] (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Incomplete translation by G. Edwards of Geochemistry (some pages missing), undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "A Study of The Tempest, by Colin Still, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Other Papers
    - Yale news release of the P.D. Ouspensky Centenary Exhibition, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 64)
- Additional Material, 1992; Accession 1993-M-034; 0.25; (1 box)
  - A Record of Meetings (held by P. D. Ouspensky between 1930 and 1947), 1992 (Box 1)
    Received from: Arkana/Penguin Books, 1992 Aug 14
  - "The Aesthetical Conceptions of P.D. Ouspensky," by Dr. V. Kravtchenko (in Russian), 1992 (Box 1)
    Received from: V. Kravtchenko, 1992 Nov 5
  - The Bridge [number 12, commemorative issue marking the fiftieth anniversary of the death of P. D. Ouspensky, published by the Society for the Study of Normal Psychology, London], 1997 (housed with Accessions 93-M-034 and 93-M-079) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Accession 1999-M-132, received from the Society for the Study of Normal Psychology, 1998
- Additonal Material, Accession 2000-M-126
  Received from Tatiana Nagro, 2000.
  - Correspondence, book manuscripts, and lecture notes (Box 1–3)
  - Lecture notes and transcripts, meeting notes (Box 4–6)
  - Research materials in binders (Box 7–9)
  - Publications [mostly books] (Box 10–16)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-014
  - Strange Life of Ivan Osokin, by P. D. Ouspensky, 1948 (Box 1)
    Received from Hein Kropholler, 2003.
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-024
  Received from William Simon, 2003.
  - Sirpaleita Tuntemattomasta Opetuksesta [Finnish translation of In Search of the Miraculous]; two copies], 2003 (Box 1)
  - Psicologia da Evolução Possível ao Homem [Portuguese translation of The Psychology of Man's Possible Evolution], [2003?]
    Accession 2004-M-032
- Additional Material, 2010; Accession 2011-M-012
  - P. D. Ouspensky y Su Teoria Espacio-Temporal Hexadimensional, by Daniel Cerqueiro, 2010 (Box 1)
    Received from Daniel Cerqueiro, 2010.